Hi. I'm here to talk about congestion,
مرحبا، سأتحدث اليوم عن الازدحام
namely road congestion.
وأعني ازدحام الطرق بالأخص
Road congestion is a pervasive phenomenon.
تعد ظاهرة ازدحام الطريق الظاهرة الاكثر انتشارا
It exists in basically all of the cities all around the world,
وهي موجودة بشكل أساسي في جميع المدن حول العالم
which is a little bit surprising when you think about it.
الأمر الذي يصبح مفاجئا عندما تبدأ التفكير به
I mean, think about how different cities are, actually.
وأعني ان تفكر في حقيقة اختلاف هذه المدن بطبيعة الحال.
I mean, you have the typical European cities,
وعلى سبيل المثال ، في المدن الأوروبية
with a dense urban core, good public transportation
التي بها مراكز مدنية مكتظة، ووسائل نقل عام جيدة
mostly, not a lot of road capacity.
وفي الغالب لا توفر طرقاتها القدرات الاستيعابية الكافية.
But then, on the other hand, you have the American cities.
من ناحية أخرى، تتميز المدن الأمريكية
It's moving by itself, okay.
بأنها ذاتية الحركة.
Anyway, the American cities:
وأعني بذلك أن المدن الأمريكية
lots of roads dispersed over large areas,
تمتلك العديد من الطرق التي تمتد لتشمل مناطق واسعة،
almost no public transportation.
دون وجود حقيقي لوسائل النقل العام.
And then you have the emerging world cities,
والان لنتحدث عن المدن الناشئة،
with a mixed variety of vehicles,
التي بها انواع مختلفة من المركبات،
mixed land-use patterns, also rather dispersed
و أنماط مختلفة من الطرق المستخدمة والمتفرقة
but often with a very dense urban core.
وبالأخص المدن ذات المراكز المدنية المكتظة.
And traffic planners all around the world have tried
وبالرغم من محاولات مسؤولي تنظيم وتخطيط حركة المرور في جميع أنحاء العالم
lots of different measures: dense cities or dispersed cities,
اتباع واستخدام تدابير مختلفة في المدن المكتظة أو المدن الممتدة على مساحات متفرقة،
lots of roads or lots of public transport
كاستخدام الكثير من الطرق أو الكثير من وسائل النقل العام
or lots of bike lanes or more information,
أو الممرات الخاصة بالدراجات أو توفير المعلومات لمستخدمي الطرق،
or lots of different things, but nothing seems to work.
وغيرها من الحلول ، ولكن يبدو انها لم تفي بالغرض.
But all of these attempts have one thing in common.
ان هذه المحاولات تشترك في شيء واحد
They're basically attempts at figuring out
وهو محاولة تعريف
what people should do instead of rush hour car driving.
مستخدمي الطرق كيفية تجنب قيادة المركبات في ساعة الذروة.
They're essentially, to a point, attempts at planning
انهم يحاولون القيام ، الى حد ما ،
what other people should do, planning their life for them.
بتخطيط ما يجب أن يقوم به مستخدمي الطرق ، وبالتالي تخطيط حياتهم اليومية.
Now, planning a complex social system
نعلم جميعا أن تخطيط أي نظام اجتماعي معقد
is a very hard thing to do, and let me tell you a story.
هو من الصعوبة بمكان واسمحوا لي ان أسرد لكم القصة التالية.
Back in 1989, when the Berlin Wall fell,
في عام 1989، عندما سقط سور برلين،
an urban planner in London got a phone call
استلم احد خبراء التخطيط المدني في لندن مكالمة هاتفية
from a colleague in Moscow saying, basically,
من زميل في موسكو يسأل بشكل أساسي،
"Hi, this is Vladimir. I'd like to know,
"مرحبا، أنا فلاديمير. أود أن أعرف،
who's in charge of London's bread supply?"
من هو المسؤول عن توفير الخبز في لندن؟
And the urban planner in London goes,
وأجاب خبير التخطيط المدني في لندن،
"What do you mean, who's in charge of London's —
ماذا تقصد، من هو المسؤول عن لندن —
I mean, no one is in charge."
أقصد، لا يوجد مسؤول."
"Oh, but surely someone must be in charge.
اه، لكن لا بد من وجود شخص مسؤول.
I mean, it's a very complicated system. Someone must control all of this."
أقصد، أنه نظام معقد . لا بد من وجود شخص مسؤول."
"No. No. No one is in charge.
"لا. لا. لا يوجد شخص مسؤول.
I mean, it basically -- I haven't really thought of it.
أقصد، في الحقيقة -- لم أفكر في الموضوع.
It basically organizes itself."
يبدو أنه ذو ذاتي التنظيم."
It organizes itself.
ذاتي التنظيم.
That's an example of a complex social system
وهذا مثال لنظام اجتماعي معقد
which has the ability of self-organizing,
له القدرة على التنظيم الذاتي،
and this is a very deep insight.
وهذه نظرة متعمقة لهذا النظام.
When you try to solve really complex social problems,
عند محاولة ايجاد حل لتحديات النظام الاجتماعي
the right thing to do is most of the time
فإنه من الصواب
to create the incentives.
ايجاد وخلق الدافع والمحفز.
You don't plan the details,
لا تقم بتخطيط التفاصيل،
and people will figure out what to do,
وسيقوم الاشخاص المعنيين بالوصول الى مفهوم معين،
how to adapt to this new framework.
والتأقلم مع النموذج الجديد.
And let's now look at how we can use this insight
لنتمعن معا في كيفية استخدام هذا المفهوم
to combat road congestion.
لمكافحة ازدحام الطرق.
This is a map of Stockholm, my hometown.
هذه خارطة ستوكهولم، مسقط رأسي
Now, Stockholm is a medium-sized city, roughly two million people,
تعتبر مدينة ستوكهولم متوسطة الحجم، يبلغ عدد سكانها مليوني نسمة،
but Stockholm also has lots of water and lots of water
وتتميز المدينة بالمسطحات المائية الكثيرة
means lots of bridges -- narrow bridges, old bridges --
والكثير من الجسور -- الجسور الضيقة، القديمة --
which means lots of road congestion.
والذي يعني كثرة ازدحام الطرق.
And these red dots show the most congested parts,
وتعبر هذه النقاط الحمراء عن مراكز الازدحام،
which are the bridges that lead into the inner city.
وهي الجسور المؤدية إلى مركز المدينة.
And then someone came up with the idea that,
ولقد اقترح احد الاشخاص
apart from good public transport,
بعيدا عن وسائل النقل العامة،
apart from spending money on roads,
وصرف المبالغ على الطرقات،
let's try to charge drivers one or two euros at these bottlenecks.
محاولة فرض رسوم بقيمة ١ أو ٢ يورو في هذه الطرق الضيقة
Now, one or two euros, that isn't really a lot of money,
والتي لا تعتبر مبلغا كبيرا
I mean compared to parking charges and running costs, etc.,
مقارنة برسوم المواقف ورسوم التشغيل الخ.،
so you would probably expect that car drivers
يمكن ان تتوقع ان يتاثر سائقو المركبات
wouldn't really react to this fairly small charge.
بهذه الرسوم المنخفضة.
You would be wrong.
هذا اعتقاد خاطئ.
One or two euros was enough to make 20 percent of cars
1 او 2 يورو كانت كافية لجعل 20 بالمئة من المركبات
disappear from rush hours.
الاختفاء في اوقات الذروة.
Now, 20 percent, well, that's a fairly huge figure, you might think,
يمكن الاعتقاد ان 20 بالمئة بالطبع هو نسبة جيدة
but you've still got 80 percent left of the problem, right?
ولكن مازال هناك 80 بالمئة من المشكلة، صحيح؟
Because you still have 80 percent of the traffic.
لانه تبقى 80 بالمئة من الازدحام.
Now, that's also wrong, because traffic happens to be
وهذا ايضا خطأ، لأن الازدحام يعتبر
a nonlinear phenomenon, meaning that
ظاهرة لا يمكن تمثيلها بشكل خطي أو متوقع
once you reach above a certain capacity threshold
حينما تتجاوز الطاقة الاستيعابية درجة معينة
then congestion starts to increase really, really rapidly.
يتزايد الازدحام بسرعة.
But fortunately, it also works the other way around.
ولكنها ايضا تعمل لحسن الحظ في الاتجاه المعاكس.
If you can reduce traffic even somewhat, then congestion
حينما تتمكن من خفض حركة المرور، بالتالي ينخفض الازدحام
will go down much faster than you might think.
بشكل سريع غير متوقع.
Now, congestion charges were introduced in Stockholm
تم بدء العمل في تطبيق رسوم الازدحام
on January 3, 2006, and the first picture here is a picture
في 3 يناير 2006 وهذه الصورة الاولى
of Stockholm, one of the typical streets, January 2.
في استوكهولم لأحد الشوارع الاعتيادية في 2 يناير.
The first day with the congestion charges looked like this.
يبدو اليوم الاول مع رسوم الازدحام
This is what happens when you take away
وهذا ما يحدث عندما تنخفض.
20 percent of the cars from the streets.
المركبات بنسبة 20 بالمئة
You really reduce congestion quite substantially.
تنخفض الازدحام بشكل ملحوظ.
But, well, as I said, I mean, car drivers adapt, right?
ولكن في الحقيقة كما قلت سابقا، يتأقلم سائقوا المركبات، صحيح؟
So after a while they would all come back because they
ليعودوا بعض وقت قصير وذلك
have sort of gotten used to charges.
لأنهم تأقلموا وتعوّدوا على الرسوم.
Wrong again. It's now six and a half years ago
ايضا خطأ. انها الان ست سنوات ونصف
since the congestion charges were introduced in Stockholm,
منذ استحداث رسوم الازدحام في ستوكهولم
and we basically have the same low traffic levels still.
ومازالت نسبة انخفاض حركة المرور منخفضة.
But you see, there's an interesting gap here in the time series
والجدير بالذكر ان هناك فجوة زمنية في تسلسل الأحداث الزمنية
in 2007.
في 2007.
Well, the thing is that, the congestion charges,
في الواقع، أن رسوم الازدحام
they were introduced first as a trial, so they were introduced
تم استحداثها بشكل تجريبي في البداية
in January and then abolished again at the end of July,
في يناير ومن ثم تم الغاءها في نهاية يوليو،
followed by a referendum, and then they were reintroduced
بناء على مذكرة استفتاء ومن ثم تم اعادة استحداثها
again in 2007, which of course was a wonderful scientific opportunity.
مرة اخرى في 2007، والتي كانت تجربة علمية جيدة.
I mean, this was a really fun experiment to start with,
لقد كانت تجربة ممتعة
and we actually got to do it twice.
وتم تفعيلها مرتين
And personally, I would like to do this every once a year or so,
شخصيا، اود تفعيل هذه التجربة مرة واحدة كل سنة
but they won't let me do that.
ولكن لن يسمح لي
But it was fun anyway.
ولكنها كانت ممتعة على كل حال
So, we followed up. What happened?
ومن ثم تابعنا، ماذا حصل؟
This is the last day with the congestion charges, July 31,
انه اليوم الاخير لرسوم الازدحام ، 31 يوليو
and you see the same street but now it's summer,
انه نفس الطريق في فصل الصيف
and summer in Stockholm is a very nice
وصيف ستوكهولم جميل جدا
and light time of the year,
في وقت خفيف من السنة،
and the first day without the congestion charges
انه اليوم الاول من غير رسوم الازدحام
looked like this.
بالشكل التالي
All the cars were back again, and you even have to admire
عادت المركبات، حتى انك تتعجب
the car drivers. They adapt so extremely quickly.
من سائقي المركبات. لقد تأقلموا بشكل سريع.
The first day they all came back.
لقد عادوا جميعا من اليوم الاول.
And this effect hanged on. So 2007 figures looked like this.
واستمروا على هذا النحو. هذه هي الاشكال والصور في 2007
Now these traffic figures are really exciting
هذه الارقام في الحقيقة مميزة
and a little bit surprising and very useful to know,
ومدهشة ومفيدة جدا
but I would say that the most surprising slide here
ولكن صفحة العرض الاكثر ادهاشا
I'm going to show you today is not this one. It's this one.
سأقوم بعرضها، ليست هذه. انها هذه.
This shows public support for congestion pricing of Stockholm,
تظهر تأييد العامة لرسوم الازدحام في ستوكهولم
and you see that when congestion pricing were introduced
وتظهر بوضوح عندما استحدثت الرسوم
in the beginning of Spring 2006, people were fiercely against it.
في بداية خريف 2006، الناس متخوفون وضد الرسوم.
Seventy percent of the population didn't want this.
70 بالمئة من السكان لم يوافقوا.
But what happened when the congestion charges
ولكن ما حدث عندما استحدثت الرسوم
were there is not what you would expect, that people hated it more and more.
كان من المتوقع، ان يكرها الناس اكثر فأكثر
No, on the contrary, they changed, up to a point
لا، بالعكس، وافقوا عليها لدرجة
where we now have 70 percent support for keeping the charges,
ان 70 بالمئة قاموا بدعم ابقاء الرسوم،
meaning that -- I mean, let me repeat that:
اعني بذلك-- سأعيد:
70 percent of the population in Stockholm
70 بالمئة من سكان ستوكهولم
want to keep a price for something that used to be free.
يودون ابقاء الرسوم لشيء كان في السابق مجاني
Okay. So why can that be? Why is that?
حسنا. لماذا هذا التغيير؟
Well, think about it this way. Who changed?
لنمعن التفكير. من تغير؟
I mean, the 20 percent of the car drivers that disappeared,
أعني ، 20 بالمئة من سائقي المركبات التي اختفت
surely they must be discontent in a way.
مستائين بطبيعة الحال
And where did they go? If we can understand this,
وأين ذهبوا؟ إن فهمنا هذا،
then maybe we can figure out how people can be so happy with this.
يمكننا أن نفهم سعادة الناس بهذا النموذج.
Well, so we did this huge interview survey
حسنا، قمنا بأخذ آراء الكثيرين
with lots of travel services, and tried to figure out
في خدمات السفريات وحاولنا فهم
who changed, and where did they go?
من الذي تغير وأين ذهبوا؟
And it turned out that they don't know themselves. (Laughter)
وتبين أنهم لا يعرفون (ضحك )
For some reason, the car drivers are --
لسبب ما، أن سائقي المركبات
they are confident they actually drive the same way that they used to do.
متأكدون فعليا من استخدامهم الطرق التي اعتادوا عليها.
And why is that? It's because that travel patterns
ولم هذا؟ لأن أنماط السفر
are much less stable than you might think.
ذات طابع أقل استقرارا مما يمكنك أن تتخيل.
Each day, people make new decisions, and people change
في كل يوم، يتم أخذ قرارا ت جديدة، ويتغير الأشخاص
and the world changes around them, and each day
ويتغير العالم حولهم،
all of these decisions are sort of nudged ever so slightly
وفي كل يوم تدفع جميع هذه القرارات
away from rush hour car driving
السائقين بعيدا عن ساعات الذروة
in a way that people don't even notice.
بشكل غير ملحوظ من الاشخاص
They're not even aware of this themselves.
ومن غير أن يشعروا بذلك.
And the other question, who changed their mind?
والسؤال الآخر، من غير فكرهم؟
Who changed their opinion, and why?
من غير رأيهم، ولماذا؟
So we did another interview survey, tried to figure out
قمنا بعمل استبيان آخر لمعرفة
why people changed their mind, and what type of group changed their minds?
لم غير الاشخاص آراءهم وأي فئة من الاشخاص غيروا آراءهم؟
And after analyzing the answers, it turned out that
وبعد تحليل الاجابات تبين
more than half of them believe that they haven't changed their minds.
انه اكثر من نصف الاشخاص لم يغيروا آراؤهم
They're actually confident that they have
انهم في الحقيقة وبكل ثقة
liked congestion pricing all along.
كانوا مع فرض رسوم الازدحام منذ البداية
Which means that we are now in a position
مما يعني اننا تمكنّا
where we have reduced traffic across this toll cordon
من خفض حركة المرور من خلال المناطق الخاضعة للرسوم
with 20 percent, and reduced congestion by enormous numbers,
بنسبة 20 بالمئة ، وانخفاض الازدحام بشكل ملحوظ
and people aren't even aware that they have changed,
دون ان يشعر الاشخاص بالتغيير
and they honestly believe that they have liked this all along.
واعتقادهم انهم كانوا مع فرض الرسوم منذ البداية
This is the power of nudges when trying to solve
هذه هي قوة الدفع عند محاولة حل
complex social problems, and when you do that,
المشاكل الاجتماعية المعقدة، وعندما تتوصل للحل
you shouldn't try to tell people how to adapt.
لا داعي لاعلام الآخرين للتأقلم
You should just nudge them in the right direction.
عليك فقط أن تدفعهم في الاتجاه الصحيح
And if you do it right,
وان فعلت ذلك بشكل صحيح
people will actually embrace the change,
سيتبنى الأشخاص هذا التغيير
and if you do it right, people will actually even like it.
حتى انهم سيعجبون بالتغيير
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا. (تصفيق)